Register of the Rusztem Vambéry Papers, 1887-1948
Hoover Institution Archives
- Speeches and Writings, 1890-1948 (Box 2-8)
  - Titled writings (Box 3)
    - Magyarország hat esztendoe eloett kinai fallal vette magát koeruel (Hungary encircled herself by a Chinese wall, six years ago), published article, Esti Kurie (Evening Courier), December 25, 1924, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Magyarság feltámadasa (Resurrection of Hungarians), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), March 27, 1932, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Memo on Hungarian democracy, unpublished, n.d., typewritten. (Box 4)
    - Memorandum on Hungary, unpublished, n.d., typewritten. (Box 4)
    - Memorandum on the prerequisites of a Danubian and/or a Balkan Federation, unpublished, n.d., typewritten. (Box 4)
    - Mit tett az angol munkáskormány? (What did the British Labour Government do?), published article, Világ (World), August 24, 1924, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Das Mitteleuropa der Juristen (The Central-Europe of jurists), published article, Berliner Tagblatt (Berlin Daily), April 7, 1916, in German., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Mors juris imperator, published article, Pesti Napló (Diary of Pest), December 25, 1913, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Mult és joevoe (Past and future), published article, Egyetemi lapok (University Bulletin), February 20, 1919, in Hungarain., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Nádosy és - Kossuth (Nádosy and - Kossuth), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), August 22, 1926, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Nagy Emil jobbágyai (Cerfs of Emil Nagy), published article, Esti Kurir (Evening Courier), January 20, 1924, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Ne védjétek meg a nemzetet - a nemzet ellen (Don't save the nation - from the nation), published, Népszava (People's Voice), December 25, 1936, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Negyven év és huszonnégy óra (Forty years and twenty-four hours), published speech, Világ (World), November 2, 1923, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Német Btk. reviziója; I. Alapelv és buentetési rendszer (Revision of the German Penal Code; I. Principles and penal system), published pamphlet, Budapest, Franklin, 1903. 91 p., in Hungarian, printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Német demokrácia és a magyar Papenek (German democracy and Hungarian Papens), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), August 7, 1932, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Nemi ragályozas veszélyének buentethetoesége (Punishability of the possible danger arisen from inflicting veneral diseases), published speech, 1917, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Népszoevetség, vagy a Népek Szoevetsége (Nation League or the League of Nations), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), May 1, 1936, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Népszoevetség koezgyuelése után (After the Session of the League of Nations), published article, Szocializmus (Socialism), November 1922, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Neueste Strafrechtsliterature in Ungarn (Most recent criminal law literature in Hungary), published article, Mitteilungen der Internationalen kriminalistischen Vereinigung, Berlin, J. Guttentag, n.d., in German., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - New York 1910-1940, published article, Ember (Man), April 29, 1939, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Notes for foreign policy Association speech, unpublished, n.d., typewritten. (Box 4)
    - Nureremberg law, unpublished, n.d., typewritten. (Box 4)
    - Numerus clausus ország (Land of numerus clausus), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), November 20, 1927, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Óda a hatalomhoz (Ode to the might), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), December 22, 1922, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Oengyilkosság a buentetoejogban (Suicide in criminal law), published article, unknown, n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 5)
    - Oereg emigránsok és fiatal Sarlósok (Old emigrants and young sickle carriers), published article Reggel (Morning), n.d. in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Oeroek erkoelcs (Eternal ethics), published article, Reggel (Morning), n.d., in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Oesterreich und Ungarn (Austria and Hungary), source unknown, n.d., in German., Clipping (Box 5)
    - Of peace and sovereignty, published article, Nation, September 10, 1946, galley proof. (Box 5)
    - Oktober 31 (October 31) published article, Ember (Man), November 4, 1939, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Oktober, a szoekevény, (October, the refugee), published article, Nepszava (People's Voice), February 12, 1928, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Orvosi titok (és a magzatelhajtás) (Medical secret (and abortus)), published article, Gyógyászat (Healing), n.d., in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Outline of a pamphlet on Central and Eastern Europe, unpublished, n.d., typewritten. (Box 5)
    - Panamarol (About corruption), published speech, Budapest, Magyar Cobden Szoevetség, January 27, 1922, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 5)
    - Párbaj (Duel), published article, Jogtudományi Koezloeny (Law Gazette), n.d., in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Párbaj mint kultúrintézmény (Duel as cultural institution), source unknown, n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 5)
    - Pazifistische Vorschlaege einer Kriminologen (Pacifistic suggestions of a criminologist), published article, Wahrheit (Truth), September 1922, in German., Printed copy. (Box 5)
    - Peace, is it possible? Unpublished, n.d., handwritten. (Box 5)
    - Pénzbuentetés mint mellékbuentetés (Fine as added penalty), published article, special issue, Jogtudomanyi Koezloeny (Law Gazette), 1905, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 5)
    - Philosemitic Nazis and antisemitic Jews; What is happening in Hungary, unpublished, n.d., handwritten. (Box 5)
    - Politikai erkoelcs (Political ethic), published, article, Népszava (People's Voice), December 25, 1930, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Problems of Central Europe, unpublished, n.d., handwritten and partly typewritten. (Box 5)
    - Radikalizmus. karácsonyi párbaj, vívja: Vambéry Rusztem (Radicalism. Christmas duel, fought by Rusztem Vambéry), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), n.d., in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Rakoczi, unpublished, n.d. in Hungarian, typewritten. (Box 5)
    - Ramsay Mac Donald, published article, Világ (World), December 1, 1922, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Regierungsplaene zur Schaffung vin Freiheits-Legionen; drei Nationen - eine Meinung (Government plans to establish Freedom Legions: three nations - same meaning), published article, Aufbau (Reconstruction), March 13, 1942, in German., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Rendes és rendkivueli (Ordinary and extraordinary), published article, Világ (World), June 22, 1924, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Rendjavaslat jogboelcselete (Jurisprudence of order proposal), published, Világ (World), December 19, 1922, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Roevid kitanitas a hazafiságról és a pacifizmusról (Short lecture on patriotism and pacifism), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), January 6, 1923, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Sajtobilincsek es sajtorabszolgak (Chains of the press, and slaves of the press), published, Népszava (People's Voice), 1927, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 5)
    - Sajtószabadság, de... (Freedom of the press, but...), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), October 30, 1932, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Sajtószabadság és békerevizió (Freedom of the Press and peace revision), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), October 9, 1927, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 5)
    - Schaechter Miksa, mint jogász (Miksa Schaechter, as a jurist), published article, Gyógyászat (Healing), n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 5)
    - Schwurgerichtsreform in Ungarn (Jury court reform in Hungary), published article, Oesterreichische Zeitschrift fuer Strafrecht, special issue, 1913, in German., Printed copy. (Box 5)
    - Secret Memorandum on Hungary, unpublished, n.d., typewritten. (Box 5)
    - Strafrecht. Die Strafgesetzgebung in Ungarn seit 1900 (Penal law. Penal law legislation in Hungary since 1900), published article, source unknown, n.d., in German., Printed copy. (Box 5)
    - Synopsis of lectures, unpublished, n.d., typewritten. (Box 5)
    - Synthesis of American and European criminology, unpublished book, n.d. (Box 5)
      - Chapter headings (Box 5)
        - Table of contents., Typewritten. (Box 5)
        - American and European prison systems., Hand- and typewritten. (Box 5)
        - Analysis of crime as a social phenomenon., Handwritten. (Box 5)
        - Capital punishment., Typewritten. (Box 5)
        - Civilization and crime. Progress of civilization and crime., Handwritten and typewritten. (Box 5)
        - Corporal punishment., Handwritten and typewritten. (Box 5)
        - Crime and criminal., Handwritten. (Box 5)
        - Crime and literature., Handwritten and typewritten. (Box 5)
        - Crime, misery and socialism., Handwritten and typewritten. (Box 5)
        - Crimanal law and morality., Handwritten. (Box 5)
        - Criminological empiricism and the science of criminology., Handwritten and typewritten. (Box 5)
        - Criminology., Handwritten and typewritten. (Box 5)
        - Curbing the habitual offender., Handwritten. (Box 5)
        - Education and crime., Handwritten. (Box 5)
        - Future of the prison, and the prison of the future., Handwritten. (Box 5)
        - Heredity and cirme., Hand- and typewritten. (Box 5)
        - How imprisonment was born., Hand- and typewritten. (Box 5)
        - How society reacts to crime., Typewritten. (Box 5)
        - Juvenile delinquents., Handwritten. (Box 5)
        - Our faith in deterrence., Hand- and typewritten. (Box 5)
        - Penological survivals., Handwritten (Box 6)
        - Prison education and labor., Hand- and typewritten. (Box 6)
        - Prison labor., Handwritten (Box 6)
        - Prison organization., Handwritten. (Box 6)
        - Race and crime., Handwritten. (Box 6)
        - Psychology of the criminal., Handwritten. (Box 6)
        - Substitutes for imprisonment., Handwritten. (Box 6)
        - On the term `Criminology.', Typewritten. (Box 6)
        - Early draft copies (Box 6)
          - Section A, parts I-XV. Drafts, typewritten. (Box 6)
          - Section B, parts, I-XVI. Drafts, typewritten. (Box 6)
          - Miscellaneous drafts and notes., Hand- and typewritten. (Box 6)
    - Szabadság és fueggetlenség (Freedom and independence), published article, n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 7)
    - Szabadság határai (Limitations of freedom), published article, n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 7)
    - Szegény ember toervénykoenyve (Poor man's law book), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), March 4,? in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Szegény káptalan és a gazdag Népszava (Poor monastery and the rich Népszava), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), August 12, 1926, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Szellemi élet szabadságáról (About the freedom of intellectual life), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), January 1, 1922, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Tanszabadság (Freedom of teaching), published article, n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 7)
    - Tanszabadság (Freedom of teaching), published article, Egyetemi lapok (Universiti Bulletin), September 7, 1890, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Tapasztalatok az Ujvilágban (Experience in the New World), published article, Budapest, November 9, 1910, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Tekintély (Prestige), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), October 9, 1932, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Tekintély és presztizs (Authority and prestige), published article, Polgár (Citizen), May 22, 1926, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Terminology, unpublished, n.d., handwritten. (Box 7)
    - Tilos az oengyilkosság (Suicide banned), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), April 29, 1928, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Toward peace on the Danube, published article, Nation, October 3, 1942, Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Unabhaengige Richter (Independent judge), published article, Pester Lloyd (Lloyd of Pest), January 9, 1922, in German., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Ungarische Jugendgerichtsentwurf (Hungarian adolescent court project), published article, Monatschrift fuer Kriminalpsychologie und Strafrechtsreform, 1913-14. Special issue., Printed copy. (Box 7)
    - Ungarisches Strafgesetzbuch und der deutsche Kommissionsentwurf (Hungarian Penal Code and the German Commission project), published article, Jogállam; Rechtsstaat (Constitutional state), 1916, special issue, in German., Printed copy. (Box 7)
    - Ungarisches Staatsrecht in Deutschland (Hungarian constitutional law in Germany), published article, Pester Lloyd (Lloyd of Pest), June 7, 1917, in German., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Választási benyomások (Election impressions), published article, Világ (World), October 25, 1924, in German., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Vambéry Rusztem beszél problemáról (Rusztem Vambéry talks about the refugee problem), published article Igazság (Justice), December 1, 1939, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Vedoe és a morál (Defender and the morale), published article, Pesti Napló (Diary of Pest), February 10, 1928, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Védvámos választás (Election with tariff protection), published, Világ (World), November 25, 1923, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - War crimes and criminals, unpublished, n.d., handwritten. (Box 7)
    - What is this war about? first and final drafts, n.d., typewritten. (Box 7)
    - What price peace? unpublished, n.d., hand- and typewritten. (Box 7)
    - Why `Totalitarian'? published article, Ember (Man), June 15, 1940, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Zsákutca és a Dunai Konfoederacio (Dead end, and the Danubian Confederation), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), December 13, 1931, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Zur Frage der Strafrechtseinheit in Deutschland, Oesterreich, and Ungarn (About the uniformity of criminal law in Germany, Austria, and Hungary), published article, Pester Lloyd (Lloyd of Pest), September 10, 1916, in German., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - Zur Vereinheitlichung des Strafsrechts; ein Widerhall in Ungarn (About the standardization of penal law; an echo from Hungary), published article, Deutsche Strafrechtszeitung (German Penal law bulletin), May-June, 1916, in German., Printed copy. (Box 7)
  - Book reviews (Box 7)
    - By R. Vambéry, a number of book reviews published in The Nation., Clippings. (Box 7)
    - By others about R. Vambéry, writings (Box 7)
      - Buentetoejog (Criminal law), Budapest, Grill, 1913. (Box 7)
      - Buenvadi perrendtartás roevid tankoenyve (Short textbook of criminal procedure), Budapest, Grill, 1909., Clipping. (Box 7)
      - Hungary to be or not to be, New York, F. Ungar, 1947, in English and Hungarian., Clippings. (Box 7)
  - Interviews (Box 7)
    - `Bajtársi szoevetség' és a háborús uszítók, Vambéry Rusztem dr. ( `Fraternity' and warmongers, Rusztem Vambéry dr.). (Box 7)
    - Beszélgetésuenk Vambéry Rusztemmel a londoni útról (Our discussion with Rusztem Vambéry about his trip to London). (Box 7)
    - Hadisegély csalások (War relief corruptions). (Box 7)
    - Hogyan kepzeli Vambéry a román-magyar koezeledés meg... (How does Vambéry immagine the Roumanian-Hungarian approachment?). (Box 7)
    - Rusztem nyilatkozat (Rusztem statement). (Box 7)
    - Vambéry Rusztem Magyarországról (Rusztem Vambéry about Hungary). (Box 7)
    - Vambéry Rusztem a toeroekoekroel (Rusztem Vambéry about the Turks). (Box 7)
    - Vámbery Rusztem kritikája az igazságugyministerroel (Rusztem Vambéry's criticism of the Minister of Justice). (Box 7)
  - Letters to the editor (Box 7)
    - General, 1941-1948 (Box 7)
    - Central European Observer,n.d., typewritten. (Box 7)
    - Gloucester Daily Times,1947, typewritten (Box 7)
    - Gyógyászat, (Healing), 1915? in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
    - New York Times,1939-1945, handwritten, typewritten, and printed copies. (Box 7)
    - Szózat, 1924, Vambéry Rusztem as informator (Rusztem Vambéry the informer) in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous drafts and notes (Box 8)
- Subject File, 1887-1947 (Box 8-9)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, lists, notes, printed matter, etc., arranged alphabetically by either subject or title.
  - American Council for Judaism, Inc., 1946 (Box 8)
  - Budapesti Koezloeny (Budapest Bulletin), July 26, 1914. (Box 8)
  - Counterfeits and counterfeiting, Hungary, 1925. (Box 8)
  - Criminal law, 1933. (Box 8)
  - Demokratidus Magyarok Amerikai Szoevetsége (American Federation of Democratic Hungarians) (Box 8)
  - Dinnyés, Prime Minister, Lajos, 1947. (Box 8)
  - Eckhardt, Tibor, 1941. (Box 8)
  - Emigránsok és újarcú emberek, (Emigrants and people with new faces), Nap (Sun), April 6, 1930, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 8)
  - Faludi, Gyoergy, Manhattan szigetén, (On Manhattan Island), and two poems, in Hungarian, n.d., Clipping. (Box 8)
  - Fényes, Lászlo, 1944. (Box 8)
  - `Fueggetlen Magyarorszaget' mozgalom és az U.S. politikája, ( `For an independent Hungary' movement, and the U.S. politics), Népszava (People's Voice) Jan. 3, 1942, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 8)
  - Hapsburg, Pretender Otto von, December 1, 1943. (Box 8)
  - Hatvany, Lajos, Kedves Vambéry Rusztem! Hét (Week), January 7, 1932, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 8)
  - Horthy, Regent of Hungary Miklós, 1947. (Box 8)
  - Hotel Van Cortland dispute, 1946-1947 (Box 8)
  - Hungary (Box 8)
    - Foreign relations, Romania, 1928 (Box 8)
    - History. (Box 8)
    - Politics and government, 1944-1947. (Box 8)
    - Social life and customs (Box 8)
    - Igazsaguegyminisztérium. Buentetoejogi Bizottság. (Hungarian Ministry of Justice. Committee on criminology), Minutes of the Session, May 12, 1947. In Hungarian, mimeographed copy. (Box 8)
  - International law (Box 8)
  - Jászi, Oszkár. 1944-1948 (Box 8)
  - Jogtudományi Koezloeny (Law Gazette), January 31, 1946, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 8)
  - Kárólyi, Count Mihály, 1942-1946, letter to Oszkár Jászi, August 6, 1946, in Hungarian. Typewritten. Also clippings in English and Hungarian. (Box 8)
  - Kemény, Gyoergy, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Koezi-Horváth, József, Halál szolgálatában, (Death service), Nemzeti Ujság (National News), September 2, 1934, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 9)
  - Kolnai, Aurél, Danubia: a survey of plans of solution, published, Journal of Central European Affairs, Vol. 3, No. 4, January 1944., Reprint. (Box 9)
  - Mi toerténjen az uralkodó osztállyal? (What shall happen to the ruling class?), Munkás (Worker), Vol. 34, No. 5, January 30, 1943, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 9)
  - Morris, William, News from nowhere,1890?, typewritten copy. (Box 9)
  - Nagy, Prime Minister Ferenc, How the Russians grabbed my government, Saturday Evening Post, Aug. 23, 30, 1947, and other clippings. (Box 9)
  - Paris, Treaty of, February 10, 1947. Bill submitted to the Parliament of Hungary, in Russian, English and Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 9)
  - Petoefi, Sándor, poems in Hungarian published in Szabadság (Liberty), n.d., Clippings. (Box 9)
  - Rajk, László, Minister of the Interior. Hungary installs virtual dictator,n.d., Clipping. (Box 9)
  - Schoenfeld, H.F. Arthur, Soviet imperialism in Hungary,n.d., printed copy. (Box 9)
  - Századunk; társadalmi szemle (Our Century; sociological review), Year 14, Nos. 4-5, May 20, 1939, in Hungarian. (Box 9)
  - Szekfue, Gyula, Valahol utat vesztettuenk (Somewhere we have lost direction), Magyar Nemzet (Hungarian Nation), January 16, 1944? in Hungarian., Photocopy of a newspaper article. (Box 9)
  - Szombati, Alexander, Lettre a Monsieur Ferenc Nagy ancien premier ministre de Hongrie (Letter to Mr. Ferenc Nagy, ex prime minister of Hungary), Volonte, November 15, 1947, in French., Printed copy. (Box 9)
  - Teleki, Count Pál. Teleki Pál beszéde a bécsi doentés uegyében a Magyar Képviseloe Házban, 1940 dec. 4-en. (Speech of Pál Teleki, Prime Minister of Hungary, concerning the Vienna Decision relative to Transylvania, delivered at the Hungarian Parliament, on September 4, 1940), quoted from the Kueluegyi Szemle (Foreign Affairs review), November 1940. In Hungarian, quoted in handwriting. (Box 9)
  - Tildy, Zoltán, President of Hungary, Tildy is pictured as critic of Nagy, New York Times, June 14, 1947, Clipping (Box 9)
  - Transylvania, History Wellesley -on the Balkans, unpublished writing of unknown authorship, n.d., typewritten. (Box 9)
  - UNESCO. General Conference, 2d Session, Minutes, October 29, 1947, in French., Mimeographed copy. (Box 9)
  - Vambéry, Armin. Clippings, in Hungarian and German, containing biographical data, relative to Armin Vambéry, the father of Rusztem Vambéry, 1887-1947. (Box 9)
  - Vambéry Rusztemektoel Macdonaldig a revizio koeruel (From the Rusztem Vambérys to Macdonald around the revision), published article, Magyarság (Hungarians), July 4, 1929, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 9)
  - World War, 1941-1945, Territorial questions, Hungary. Szabadság és a régi magyar határok (Freedom and the old Hungarian frontiers), Amerikai magyar népszava (American Hungarian People's Voice), n.d., in Hungairan., Clippings. (Box 9)
  - Zionists. Political Zionists exploit untruth about Palestine, New York Herald Tribune, May 2, 1946., Clipping. (Box 9)
  - Zoltán, Mirjam, typewritten letter, n.d., in Hungarian. (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous Clippings. 1911-1948. (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings. (Box 9)